

#### RESEARCHER IN COMPUTATIONAL TRUST, PRIVACY AND SECURITY

Diasta Ekoda no Mori 503, 2-20-3 Toyotama-kita, Nerima-ku, Tokyo 176-0012, Japan

□ (+81) 80-3315-8649 | ■ a.basu@xtremebytes.com | ♠ http://www.anirbanbasu.com | ₲ anirbanbasu | ᠖ a.basu

# **Summary**\_

With over a decade of research experience within both academia and industry, I have co-authored over 70 research papers and over 20 Japanese patent applications. My research is based on a user-centric view of privacy and computational trust as an information security paradigm in an increasingly knowledge-based connected world. I like building things to solve real-world problems. Outside research and problem solving, I am keen on photography, videography and the associated travels.

# Professional experience \_\_\_

### KDDI Research (erstwhile KDDI R&D Laboratories)

Fujimino, Japan

SENIOR RESEARCHER

May. 2013 – present

- *Highlights:* Enhancing a portfolio of research in the multidisciplinary area of privacy, security, computational trust and knowledge in distributed computing, which now contains over 20 patent applications and over 70 research papers.
- Selected projects: (a) A multi-institutional EUR 3M EU-Japan Horizon 2020 funded project to realise a secure data storage and privacy-preserving analytics engine over heterogeneous multi-cloud environments spanning across national borders; (b) a multi-institutional JPY 375M Japanese government project on applied security and privacy in big data; and (c) a Toyota ITC and KDDI Research jointly funded collaborative project with ISTI-CNR and the University of Pisa on privacy risks in trajectory data.

Sole proprietorship Tokyo, Japan

MOBILE APPS DEVELOPER AND TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT

Aug. 2014 – present

- Highlights: Developing software, games and providing technology consultancy. My main full-time position is with KDDI Research.
- Selected project: An application to help users 'remember' complex passwords: http://pa55.github.io/pa55nyaps/.

Tokai University Tokyo, Japan

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Oct. 2010 – Mar. 2013

- Highlights: Proposed a privacy-preserving collaborative filtering scheme over encrypted domain and demonstrated the feasibility in real-world public cloud environments the Google App Engine and the Amazon Elastic Beanstalk.
- Project: A multi-institutional JPY 500M+ Japanese government funded project on privacy-preserving data mining on the cloud.

#### **University of Sussex**

Brighton, UK

ASSOCIATE TUTOR (OCT. 2004 – JAN. 2010) AND RESEARCH FELLOW (OCT. 2008 – SEP. 2009)

Oct. 2004 – Jan. 2010

- *Highlights:* Re-developed a course module on electronic commerce technologies for the Masters degree programme funded by American Express, which was ranked amongst the top course modules in the department.
- Projects: Two (GBP 1M and GBP 1.4M) EPSRC funded research projects related to computational trust.

Various organisations Brighton, UK

TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT (JUL. 2005 – SEP. 2008; JUN. 2010 – SEP. 2010)

Jul. 2005 - Sep. 2010

• Highlights: Worked twice as a technology consultant to the University of Sussex library. Developed Web Services hooks for an existing Java EE solution for Class Calendar Ltd. Co-developed computational skills training videos for Claro Training Ltd.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

STEP SUMMER INTERN (JUL. 2003 – Aug. 2003) and then Research Assistant

Jul. 2003 - Sep. 2004

- *Highlights:* Conceived and built a lightweight augmented reality based visualisation technology based on backend XML-based storage. Submitted (and later published) 4 international conference papers before finishing the Bachelor degree.
- *Project*: €2.8M EU Framework Programme V funded project on digital cultural heritage.
- Award: Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP, UK) Local Finalist.

## **Professional affiliations**

**IFIPTM** Tokyo, Japan

Publicity Chair (Jun. 2010 – Jun. 2015) and Secretary (Jun. 2015 – Present)

Jun. 2010 - present

• Summary: Formerly the Publicity Chair, now serving as the Secretary of the premier venue on computational trust management – the IFIP Working Group 11.11.

Rutgers University
VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

Newark, NJ, USA

Oct. 2014 – present

• **Summary:** Working on collaborative research with Prof. Jaideep Vaidya within the Institute for Data Science, Learning, and Applications (I-DSLA). This position does not require me to be based in the USA.

**University of Sussex** 

Brighton, UK

VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

Jan. 2010 – present

• **Summary:** Working on collaborative research within the Foundations of Software Systems (FoSS) group at the Department of Informatics. This position does not require me to be based in the UK.

<sup>&</sup>quot;There is only one corner of the universe you can be certain of improving, and that's your own self." – Aldous Huxley

### **Education**

### University of Sussex Brighton, UK

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (D.PHIL.) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE

Oct. 2004 - Feb. 2010

- Supervisors: Prof. Ian Wakeman and Dr. Dan Chalmers.
- Examiners: Dr. Des Watson (University of Sussex) and Prof. David Parish (Loughborough University)
- Doctoral thesis: 'A Reputation Framework for Behavioural History' proposed a high-level, generalised, policy-independent and context-aware framework to build and share reputations of network clients based on their behavioural history in order to inform future interactions. PDF: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-dphil2010.pdf.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING (B.ENG.) IN COMPUTER SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Oct. 2001 – Jun. 2004

- Grade: First Class Honours.
- Awards: (1) IEE Sussex Branch local prize for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.); and (2) the Eurotherm company prize for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project.
- Final year project: 'ARCOLite a visualisation system for viewing museum artefacts' presented a lightweight XML-based repository and a desktop visualisation in both virtual and augmented reality. PDF: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-beng2004.pdf.

## **Accolades**

### INVITED TALKS

2017	IFIP TM – Doctoral Symposium, Homomorphic Encryption – an answer to privacy?	Göteborg, Sweden
2015	<b>Kyushu University - Next Generation Cryptography</b> , Homomorphic Encryption - are we there yet?	Fukuoka, Japan
2012	<b>CSA – SecureCloud</b> , Practical privacy using homomorphic encryption – a myth or reality	Frankfurt, Germany

#### **AWARDS**

2004	<b>IEE Sussex Branch local prize</b> , for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.)	Brighton, UK
2004	Eurotherm company prize, for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project	Brighton, UK
2003	Local Finalist, Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP)	Brighton, UK

#### SCHOLARSHIPS

2004–2007 <b>Graduate Teaching Assistantship</b> , Department of Informatics (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK
2001–2004 <b>Dean's Bursary</b> , Department of Engineering and Design (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK

## **Publications**

A full list of publications is available at: http://www.anirbanbasu.com/#research.

#### **Research papers**

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] K. Suksomboon, A. Tagami, **A. Basu**, and J. Kurihara, "IPRES: in-device proxy re-encryption service for secure ICN," in *Proceedings of the 4th ACM Conference on Information-Centric Networking (ICN)*. Berlin, Germany: ACM, 2017, pp. 176–177.
- [2] **A. Basu**, M. S. Rahman, R. Xu, K. Fukushima, and S. Kiyomoto, "VIGraph A Framework for Verifiable Information," in *Proceedings of the IFIP WG 11.11 International Conference on Trust Management (IFIPTM)*, Göteborg, Sweden, 2017, pp. 12–20.
- [3] **A. Basu**, A. Monreale, R. Trasarti, J. C. Corena, F. Giannotti, D. Pedreschi, S. Kiyomoto, Y. Miyake, and T. Yanagihara, "A risk model for privacy in trajectory data," *Journal of Trust Management*, vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 1–23, 2015.
- [4] J. Vaidya, I. Yakut, and **A. Basu**, "Efficient Integrity Verification for Outsourced Collaborative Filtering," in *Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Data Mining (ICDM)*, Shenzhen, China, 2014.
- [5] **A. Basu**, J. Vaidya, H. Kikuchi, and T. Dimitrakos, "Privacy-preserving collaborative filtering on the cloud practical implementation experiences," in *Proceedings of the IEEE Cloud*, Santa Clara, CA, USA, 2013.
- [6] A. Basu, S. Fleming, J. Stanier, S. Naicken, I. Wakeman, and V. K. Gurbani, "The state of peer-to-peer network simulators," *ACM Computing Surveys*, vol. 45, no. 4, pp. 46:1–46:25, 08 2013.
- [7] **A. Basu**, I. Wakeman, and D. Chalmers, "A Framework for Developing and Sharing Client Reputations," in *Proceedings of the IFIP WG 11.11 International Conference on Trust Management (IFIPTM)*, Morioka, Japan, 2010.

## Patents (including pending) and public information

JAPAN PATENT OFFICE APPLICATION NUMBERS

2013-141965, 2013-171600, 2013-202289, 2013-232080, 2013-272722, 2014-020802, 2014-054142, 2014-094155, 2014-149798, 2014-128201, 2014-17250, 2015-158205, 2015-046346, 2015-180642, 2016-066512, 2017-018877, 2017-018878, 2017-029170, 2017-029171, 2017-029172, 2017-099572, 2017-096380, 2017-198726, 2018-001096.

# Skills

OS: MacOS, Windows, Linux, UNIX; Documents: MS Office, Google Docs and EtX; Software development: Java, C#, Objective-C, Computing skills

C++, Visual C++, C, Visual Basic, XML, Javascript, UML, Subversion, Git, JUnit, Ant, Maven, MySQL, JBoss, Tomcat, Google App

Engine, Amazon Elastic Beanstalk. (Non-exhaustive list.)

Languages English (fluent), Bengali (native), Japanese (elementary), Hindi (elementary)

UPDATED: JANUARY 15, 2018 ANIRBAN BASU | CURRICULUM VITÆ 2 OF 2